Okay. בוקר
טוב. Boker tov. All right. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf
is יא, Yud Aleph, 11. We pick up at the very bottom
of י עמוד ב Yud Amud Bet and we once again return
to the
משנה. mishna. I hope you'll find today's discussion relatively straightforward compared to
the last few days. So four lines from the bottom, אם יש
לו צורת הפתח, im yesh lo tzurat hapetach, like the משנה mishna
said that a מבוי mavoi can't be higher than 20 or wider
than 10, and now it starts talking about ways to solve that
problem. So אם יש לו צורת הפתח, im yesh lo tzurat hapetach,
quoting from the משנה, mishna, if there's a door frame, which as
we know is two posts and a beam on top,
then אף על פי שרחב מעשר אין צריך למעט. af al pi
sherachav me'eser ein tzarich lema'et. We discussed yesterday how to make the
opening smaller by making
a lengthwise plank that divides the מבוי mavoi in two, or more
simply by closing off part of the opening and how much of
the opening you have to close off. But here we say if
you make a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, then you don't have to.
That defines the whole opening no matter how big it is as
an opening because it's got as a frame, as a door, because
it has a frame around it, and it doesn't matter how wide
it is. And as I've mentioned to you before, this is very
relevant for practical הלכה, halacha, because you go out into the streets
and how do we make our עירוב eruv in the city is
we make it by
doorframes, by banging beams into posts against the telephone pole
and using the telephone wire, and we have huge צורות הפתח tzurot
hapetach that surround the entire area and that's good, and that assumes
that you can have a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach bigger than 10
אמות. amot. By the way, the רמב״ם Rambam rules, just so you're
aware, that a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach doesn't help for bigger than
10 אמות. amot. So according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, you really cannot
have a contemporary עירוב. eruv.
Wait, but the word is פתח, petach, right, like a door?
That's the argument, but the משנה mishna says at least with that
even if the door is bigger than 10 אמות amot you can
use a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. So now we're going to see
the discussion about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
So where's A, where does רמב״ם Rambam get?
Well let's read today's גמרא Gemara and then you'll have the answer.
Okay. And second they did go to רמב״ם Rambam עירוב eruv in
Philadelphia.
Did they really? Center City. Oh my god.
Okay. 167 years ago.
Okay. אשכחן Ashkachan says the גמרא, Gemara, two lines on the bottom,
אשכחן צורת הפתח דמהני ברחבה. ashkachan tzurat hapetach d'mahani berachvah.
We see that a doorframe helps if it's too wide. That's the
משנה. mishna. דאמלטרא, D'amaltara, you might remember the אמלטרא amaltara going back
to the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, which was like the cornice,
the fancy carving at the top and or at the corners above,
that the גמרא Gemara quoted at the beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
דמהני בגבהו, d'mahani begavho, that even if it's higher than 20 it's
such a fancy carving in the corner of the frame that everybody
looks up and even if it's very high it's okay. So we
know that from our earlier discussion. So now the גמרא Gemara top
of יא עמוד א Yud Aleph Amud Aleph says, איפכא מאי? ipcha
mai? What about the reverse? Will a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach help
if it's too high? And will a cornice help if it's too
wide? And you understand the logic why maybe
not, because too high the problem is you don't see it so
the cornice makes you see it. It's not clear why that would
help if the problem is too wide, that it's just too big
to be defined as a doorframe. Or צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach might
help to define it as a doorframe, but again if the problem
is too high is
a problem about being visible, not so clear how צורת הפתח tzurat
hapetach is going to help for that. So that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. Can it work in the reverse?
So תא שמע tashma come and hear, דתניא d'tanya we learn in
a ברייתא, baraita, מבוי שהוא גבוה מעשרים אמה ימעט, mavoi she'hu gavo'ah
me'esrim amah yema'et, a מבוי mavoi that's higher than 20 אמות amot
you have to lower, ואם יש לו צורת הפתח v'im yesh lo
tzurat hapetach but if it has a doorframe אינו צריך למעט eno
tzarich lema'et you don't have to. So look at that, a צורת
הפתח tzurat hapetach helps even higher than 20 אמה, amah, not clear
why. Maybe it's because the problem, maybe it's because it's an issue
of היכר heker and if you have the bar beam on the
side that starts going up it encourages you to look all the
way up, who knows? Or maybe because it's not about היכר heker
at all, maybe it's about defining it as a door and therefore
a doorframe helps define it as a door even if it's higher
than 20 אמה. amah. Okay.
Now by the way תוספות Tosafot asks a question. תוספות Tosafot says
I don't get it. Who needs the
doorframe to work higher than 20 אמה? amah? If you have a
doorframe what's a doorframe? A beam here, a beam here, a post
here, a post here and a beam on top. So he says
who cares that the beam on top is higher than 20 אמה?
amah? If you have a post here and a post here you
have a לחי, lechi, right? So a לחי lechi should be enough.
So why does it matter that it's higher than 20 אמה? amah?
So he has a few answers. One answer is that maybe the
לחי lechi is too thin, maybe it's an opinion that you need
a לחי lechi to be a certain thickness and it's less than
that
thickness, okay, or the case where like I gave you an example,
not by a מבוי mavoi where a לחי lechi is enough, a
case where you really need a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, so talking
about a different scenario like you're outdoors and the street is wide
open and you need a
צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, and a לחי lechi wouldn't be enough. So
that's the answer that a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, this is very
relevant, works even wider than 10 and even higher than 20. higher
than twenty. Now, אמתצור ברחבו מאי? amtzur berachvo mai? How about this
cornice if it's too wide, will that help? And there you can
see the logic to say no. I mean, why should a cornice
help if it's too wide? So תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear, דתניא, detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: braita: מבוי
שהוא גבוה מעשרים אמה ימעט. mavoi shehu gavoha me'esrim ama yema'et. If
a מבוי mavoi is wider than
twenty—I'm sorry, lower. If it's higher than twenty אמה, ama, so you
have to make it lower. ורחב מעשר ימעט, verachav me'eser yema'et, wider
than ten, you have to make it narrower. ואם יש לו צורת
הפתח אינו צריך למעט. ve'im yesh lo tzurat hapetach eino tzarich lema'et.
If it has a doorframe, you do not have to make it
narrower. ואם יש לו אמתצור אינו צריך למעט. ve'im yesh lo amtzur
eino tzarich lema'et. And if it has a cornice, you do not
have to make it less. So, what's the case where you don't
have to make it less with a cornice? מאי לאו אסיפא? mai
lav aseifa? Is it not talking about the last case where the
problem is that it's too wide and the cornice helps? לא, ארישא.
lo, areisha. Not necessarily. Maybe the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is talking
about the too wide case, but maybe the cornice is talking about
the too high case. So we cannot prove whether a cornice will
help if it's too wide, and there's a good argument to say
that it shouldn't, that there's no good logic why the cornice should
help if it's too wide. Okay, so that's the issue about what
are the, whether the solution of צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach and cornice
works. What's key for us is that the גמרא Gemara has emphasized
that צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach works not just for too wide, but
even for too high. Very relevant for us for using a צורת
הפתח. tzurat hapetach. But now we're going to see a debate around
the צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. And we quoted this גמרא Gemara earlier
as well. מתני לה רב יהודה לחייא בר רב קמיה דרב. matni
lah Rav Yehuda le-Chiyya bar Rav kamei de-Rav. So רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda taught חייא בר רב, Chiyya bar Rav, רב's Rav son, in
the presence of רב, Rav, he taught our משנה mishna the way
we have it written: אינו צריך למעט, eino tzarich lema'et, that if
you have a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, you don't have to make
it narrower. צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach helps. אמר ליה, amar lei, and
רב Rav corrected him and say, excuse me, אתניה, atneiye, you should
teach it to him: צריך למעט, tzarich lema'et, that even with a
צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, you have to make it narrower, which would
be funny that the משנה mishna would say that. You know, the
משנה mishna presumably would tell you how to fix it, but anyway,
רב's Rav version of the משנה mishna is: צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
does not help, and צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach you have to make
it narrower. So according to רב, Rav, a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
is not good if it is less than—if it is more than
ten אמות. amot. And that, by the way, is the ruling of
the רמב"ם, Rambam, not our ruling. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, so said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, מדברי רבינו נלמד, midivrei Rabbeinu
nilmad, from the words of our master, meaning רב, Rav, who says
a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does not work on bigger than—on wider
than ten אמות, amot, we can learn that חצר שרובה פתחים וחלונות.
chatzer she-rubba petachim ve-chalonot. If you have a courtyard, the majority of
which is windows and doors and openings, meaning that the problem is
that it is—it is פרוץ מרובה על העומד, parutz merubba al ha-omed,
more opening than wall. Right? We discussed a lot of that yesterday.
כהאי גוונא, ke-hai gavna, something of that nature. So you have a
courtyard that is of that nature. Now, can you close off those
openings with a צורת הפתח? tzurat hapetach? Now, again, let me refer
you to our current reality. That's exactly what we do. You walk
outside, it's certainly פרוץ מרובה על העומד, parutz merubba al ha-omed, there's
no עומד. omed. Okay, if there's עומד, omed, it's a few little
telephone poles. Okay, it's ninety-nine percent פרוץ, parutz, and we close it
all off with a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. So here's the question:
the same רב Rav that says צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does not
work for more than ten אמה, ama, what would he say—would it
work for פרוץ מרובה על העומד parutz merubba al ha-omed if the
majority is open? So he's going to say, from the רב's Rav
ruling that it does not work for more than ten אמה, ama,
we can infer that חצר שרובה פתחים וחלונות, chatzer she-rubba petachim ve-chalonot,
if you have a courtyard the majority of which is openings and
windows, אינן ניתרות בצורת הפתח. einan nitarot be-tzurat hapetach. Even if those
openings and windows are less than ten אמה, ama, a צורת הפתח
tzurat hapetach does not work. For him, צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is
very limited, does not work for more than ten אמה, ama, does
not work if the majority is unwalled. Okay. And how do you
know that? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the—what's the reason that I
say that? הואיל ויותר מעשר אוסר במבוי. ho'il ve-yoter me-eser oser be-mavoi.
We know that a—a gap more than ten אמה ama is a
problem in a מבוי, mavoi, right? More than ten אמה, ama, we've
discussed, is—you know, no longer considered a door, it's a problem. ופרוץ
מרובה על העומד אוסר בחצר. u-parutz merubba al ha-omed oser be-chatzer. And
when the majority is—is פרוץ, parutz, is unwalled, that's a problem in
a חצר. chatzer. Okay, why we're associating one specifically with a מבוי,
mavoi, one specifically with a חצר, chatzer, we won't worry about right
now. You know, we've discussed a little bit that before. It's not
so much מבוי mavoi and חצר, chatzer, but is it lengthwise or
widthwise? Anyway, we won't worry about that exact division. But the point
is we know that ten אמה ama is a problem, we know
that פרוץ מרובה parutz merubba is a problem. Okay, so
מה יותר מעשר האוסר במבוי אינו ניתר בצורת הפתח, mah yoter me-eser
ha-oser be-mavoi eino nitar be-tzurat hapetach, the same way צורת הפתח tzurat
hapetach does not solve the wider than ten אמה ama gap like
we've been saying according to
רב, Rav, אף פרוץ מרובה על העומד, af parutz merubba al ha-omed,
so similarly when it's more—when the majority is
unwalled, האוסר בחצר אינו ניתר בצורת הפתח. ha-oser be-chatzer eino nitar be-tzurat
hapetach. צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach won't solve. צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does
not solve, according to רב, Rav, problems. So therefore, it's—you know, it
works like a לחי lechi or a קורה, korah, but it doesn't
solve something as fundamentally problematic. So if it is too big, if
it is too wide, or there's too much opening, it won't solve
it. That's his answer. That's his argument. So the גמרא Gemara pushes
back. So the גמרא Gemara says, no מאי יתיר מעשר האוסר במבוי
שכן לא הותרה אצלו פסי בירות לרבי מאיר. mai yatir me'eser ha'oser
bemavoi sheken lo hutra etzlo patzei birot le'Rabbi Meir. One minute, I
understand why a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach might not work for a
opening more than עשר אמות, eser amot, because there's other places that
we are very strict about gaps more than עשר אמות. eser amot.
For example, the פסי בירות. patzei birot. Remember the פסי בירות patzei
birot was like the corners around the well? So we said yesterday
the gap between the opening could be thirteen and a third אמה.
amah. Okay, that was according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says the gap even by the פסי בירות patzei
birot could only be up to עשר. eser. So now what do
you have by פסי בירות? patzei birot? You have only these little
corners, the majority is un-walled, so we're lenient on the fact that
the majority is un-walled, but we still demand that the gaps be
עשר אמות eser amot or less. So you see where we're allowed
to, we're more lenient when it comes to the idea of being
majority un-walled than we are when it comes to the size of
the gap. So therefore, maybe a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach will work
for the majority un-walled, because that's an area where generally tend to
be more lenient about. Okay, so let's read that. מאי יתיר מעשר
האוסר במבוי? mai yatir me'eser ha'oser bemavoi? More than עשר eser is
a problem in a מבוי. mavoi. Not only that is it a
problem in a מבוי, mavoi, but שכן לא הותרה אצלו פסי בירות
לרבי מאיר. sheken lo hutra etzlo patzei birot le'Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir does not allow gaps more than עשר eser in פסי
בירות. patzei birot. So therefore we're going to be very strict and
say צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach doesn't work. תאמר בפרץ מרובה על העומד?
Tomar befarutz meruba al ha'omed? But will you necessarily say the same
thing when the majority is un-walled? העושה בחצר, ha'oseh bechatzer, it's true
that is a problem in a חצר, chatzer, but שכן הותרה אצלו
פסי בירות. sheken hutra etzlo patzei birot. לדברי הכל, Ledivrei hakol, everybody
agrees that that's okay by the well, because the whole idea of
the well is you just have the corners and the majority is
un-walled. So since we are lenient at least in the case of
the well by the case of majority un-walled, maybe that is a
lesser problem and can be solved even by a צורת הפתח. tzurat
hapetach.
Now why is that?
So, okay, why, I'll talk in a minute. But anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara does not conclude that way, but it's not clear what
the conclusion is. But it basically says, according to רב, Rav, a
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does not work for bigger than עשר אמות.
eser amot. It might work for the case of majority un-walled, not
clear. Now why is there a difference? At least why is there
a difference for צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach helping, it's not hard to
understand. Because the argument that צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does not help
for bigger than עשר eser is conceptually צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is
saying we're defining this as a doorway. So you could say, look,
if it's too big, you can't call it a doorway. I don't
care that you've got a doorframe. It's not a doorway, it's too
large. It's just an open, it's like, it's a breach. It's a
breach. Alright. But that at least is the
argument. Whereas פרוץ מרובה parutz meruba is not saying that I can't
conceptualize this as a doorway. It's just saying there's too much un-walled.
But once I can fundamentally say I can call it a doorway,
then it stops being considered un-walled. If it's a doorway, then it's
as if the wall continues through this place. It's not like it's
a breach. So you can understand why that can work. When you
directly come to solve the local problem, I'm creating a doorframe in
this gap. Does it define this as a doorway or not? If
it's too wide, you could say no. But if it's not too
wide, you could say yes. And now that I've defined it, I
have a hundred doorways, I don't have a problem of having breaks
in my wall, because I have doorways in my wall. So the
logic of saying it works by that case and not by the
too wide makes a lot of sense, although that is debated whether
רב Rav would apply his limit even to the case of too
exposed.
Okay, so פסי בירות, patzei birot, the היתר heter is from, you
can't have the opening too large, but you can have majority... Right,
so פסי בירות, patzei birot, it's not the same point because by
פסי בירות patzei birot you're not creating a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach.
You're just saying the whole thing is okay. And there what you're
saying is that since you have the frame, it defines the corners,
it defines the whole thing as enclosed even though when you look
at it more micro, you know there's big gaps.
Why there we'd be more strict by the size of the gap
than the totality is maybe a different issue. But at least for
the question about the use of the צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, you
can certainly hear what the difference could be. Okay, לימא מסייע ליה.
Leima mesayeya lei. Now the גמרא Gemara says, let me come and
try to prove to you that a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach does
not work if it's too much
exposed. It hasn't proved it, but it wants to prove the stricter
read of רב. Rav. Not only does it not work if it's
too wide, it doesn't work if it's mostly exposed. דפנות הללו שרובן
פתחים וחלונות, Defanot hallalu sheruban petachim vechalonot,
if you have walls, the majority of which are openings and windows,
meaning are not walled in, מותר, mutar, you can use them, ובלבד
שעומד מרובה על הפרוץ, u'vilvad she'omed meruba al haparutz, as long as
the majority is walled. So the גמרא Gemara says, what are you
talking about? That line didn't make any sense. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
שרובן סלקא דעתך? sheruban salka datach? The majority is un-walled? How does
it read? If the majority is breaks, it's okay as long as
the majority is walled. Right? Obviously that doesn't make sense. It started
by saying if the majority is breaks, it's okay as long as
the majority is walled. So what do you mean? אלא אימא, Ela
eima, it doesn't mean the majority is breaks. It means אלא אימא
שריבה בהם פתחים וחלונות. ela eima sheriba bahem petachim vechalonot. You have
a multiplicity, you have many... Many, if you have a wall that
has many breaks and windows, it's okay ובלבד שהן עומד מרובה על
הפרוץ uvelvad sheheym omed meruba al haparutz as long as it's a
majority is walls. Okay, so anyway what's the point? The point is
look, why did we have to why does that have to be
true? If you have doorways, then the doorways presumably have doorframes, right?
It didn't say you have breaks. It said פתחים p'chahim doorways. So
if you have doorways, you have doorframes. So why is it that
even with doorways, you need to have the majority to be walls?
It sounds like a צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach does not help if
the majority is openings. So you see isn't that a good proof
that צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach does not help for that? So אמר
רב כהנא amar Rav Kahana says רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, כי תניא
ההיא בפתחי שימאי. ki tanya hi b'pichai shimai. No, we're talking when
we talk about those we're talking about like like
destroyed doorways. מאי פתחי שימאי, mai pichai shimai, what does destroyed doorways
mean? פליגי בה רב רחומי ורב יוסף. pligi bah Rav Rechumi v'Rav
Yosef. So it's a debate of רב רחומי Rav Rechumi and רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. חד אמר chad amar one says דלית להו שקפי,
d'leit lehu shikfei, it does not have
משקוף, mashkof, but we say משקוף mashkof is lintel, right? רש"י Rashi
says here the שקפי shikfei the משקוף mashkof it means the actually
the the side, the doorframe. רש"י Rashi says what it means is
that the door how could how could a door way not have
a doorframe? רש"י Rashi says it's like jutting in and out like
this, you know? So basically it doesn't have a straight like the
you know the stones come in and out. It's not flush. So
therefore this can't count as a doorframe because it's not a flush
side. Okay, so there it's not a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapetach. He
says or וחד אמר דלית להו תקרא, v'chad amar d'leit lehu tikra,
it
doesn't have a roof, meaning it does not have a lintel. So
yes, it's a break in the wall. In the end what they're
saying is it means a break in the wall. It does not
mean a doorframe. If you actually have a doorframe, it could count
even if it's the majority. We're talking that it's a break in
the wall and that's why it doesn't count. So now we have
this extremely important debate: does a צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach work if
it's bigger than ten and does it work if it's the majority
is exposed? And both of those leniencies is what we rely on
to create our current eruvs. So let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara says. ואף רב יוחנן סבר לה להא דרב, v'af Rav
Yochanan savar lah l'ha d'Rav, even רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds of
רב Rav that a doorframe does not work if it's wider than
ten.
So we have a lot of people seeming to back רב Rav
limiting צורת הפתח. tzuras hapetach. דאמר רבין בר רב אדא אמר רב
יצחק, d'amar Ravin bar Rav Adda amar Rav Yitzchak, so רבין בר
רב אדא Ravin bar Rav Adda says in the name of רב
יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, מעשה באדם אחד מביקעת בית חורתן, maaseh b'adam echad
m'bik'at Beit Chortan, a story of a certain man that came from
this place, the valley of בית חורתן, Beit Chortan, שנעץ ארבע קונדיסין
בארבע פינות השדה, shenatz arba kundisin b'arba pinot hasadeh, he stuck four
posts in the four corners of a field, ומתח זמורה עליהם umataich
zmora aleihem and he stretched a vine on top of them. And
basically he was planting like it was a vineyard. So basically, he
just simply he stuck here he had his rows or I don't
know of grape vines and he stuck four posts here and he
stretched a vine around that. And he wanted to say this is
its own zone and I can plant wheat and other stuff I
can plant here because even though it's right nearby, if it's separated
by a wall or a halachic
wall, right? צורת הפתח, tzuras hapetach, you can plant right next to
it. That's an astonishing ruling. So yes, so because a lot of
כלאים kilayim has to do with visual and not just with the
reality on drawing on the same nutrients. So here basically you have
four צורת הפתח, tzuras hapetachs, it's the perfect example of what we
do for our eruvs, where it's the entire part is exposed. Can
a צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach work if you are dealing with majority
or in this case entirety
un-walled? So that's the case. So let's take a look.
And that's dealing with a biblical issue.
Right, right. So he said so he put in these four posts
בארבע פינות השדה b'arba pinot hasadeh the four corners ומתח זמורה עליהם,
umataich zmora aleihem, he strung a vine on top of them ובא
מעשה לפני חכמים והתירו לו לענין כלאים. u'ba maaseh lifnei chachamim v'hitiru
lo l'inyan kilayim.
And the rabbis allowed it said fine for כלאים kilayim that's fine
you can plant other other seeds right next to it. ואמר ריש
לקיש v'amar Reish Lakish said ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, כשם שהתירו לו
לענין כלאים keshem shehitiru lo l'inyan kilayim the same way
they allowed it for purposes of כלאים, kilayim, כך התירו לו לענין
שבת. kach hitiru lo l'inyan Shabbos.
If you had a similar case by שבת Shabbos that would be
fine you could carry in that zone and that's obviously exactly what
we do. We make everything a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapetach. רב יוחנן
אמר, Rav Yochanan amar, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says and he's the
one we think holds like רב Rav who's more restrictive. No, רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan says לכלאים התירו לו l'kilayim hitiru lo for כלאים
kilayim it was okay ולענין שבת לא התירו לו. u'l'inyan Shabbos lo
hitiru lo. Not for שבת. Shabbos. Okay, במאי עסקינן? b'mai askinan? Now
what's the case, what's the point? I described that the challenge here
was was that the majority or the entirety was unwalled. Let's see
how the גמרא Gemara frames what the issue is. במאי עסקינן? b'mai
askinan? What are we talking? אילימא מן הצד? eileima min hatzad? Now
the גמרא Gemara
says maybe the problem had nothing to do with how much was
exposed. Maybe it had to do with the fact that he did
not put the beam on top, he put the beam on the
side, right? That's what I've been telling you and we're going to
see about this in it right now about where does the beam
have to be for a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. The problem was
using the telephone wires as they exist, right, because how does a
telephone pole work? It's got this stuff, right, and the wires go
like that and the wires do not go directly on top of,
right, even if it's even if the wire comes off of here,
it does not go directly on top. So that's the question. If
you have a צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, right, and he did this
זמורה, zmora, he did this vine, that would be okay, but it's
more likely you would think that he would probably wrap the vine
around the post, right? And if you wrap the vine around the
post like that, that's no good. That's מן הצד min hatzad and
that's not a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. So the גמרא Gemara thinks
maybe that is the problem. Maybe the problem here and the issue
of whether it works for שבת Shabbos is when the beam goes
on the side and not on the top. If you have an
actual door, even if like the it goes further up, let's say
your door is just a little bit... well, a door is a
wall, so a door is actually closed off. So, okay. אילימא מן
הצד? eileima min hatzad? What? That would be the same thing as
a gate then? What? That would be the same thing as a
gate then, a gate is actually closed off too? If you actually,
yeah, if you actually have the physical gate and not just the
frame. This is why then a gate can be wider than... right.
So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. אילימא מן הצד, eileima
min hatzad, let's say the issue here whether it worked for שבת
Shabbos or not was that the beam went the vine went by
the side. ואמר רב חסדא, va'amar Rav Chisda, that can't be. צורת
הפתח שעשאה מן הצד לא עשה ולא כלום, tzuras hapesach she'asa'a min
hatzad lo asa velo klum, that everybody would agree that that's worthless
even for שבת, Shabbos, or ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, in at least
for שבת Shabbos it's worthless. So there's no way ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish could have said that that's good. אלא על גביו, ela al
gabav, it must be that the vine went on top and even
so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had a problem. So if the vine
went on top, what would רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's problem have been?
ובמאי, uv'mai, and what was the case? אילימא בעשר, eileima b'eser, if
it was ten or less, והאמר רבי יוחנן בשבת לא? ve'ha'amar Rabbi
Yochanan beShabbos lo? Why would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say it's not
good by שבת? Shabbos? Now you could have said the problem is
that it was all exposed, but the גמרא Gemara is now focusing
in on the question of ten or more than ten. So if
it was the side, there's no way ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would
have said it's good. If it was on the top and less
than ten, no, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, he said it is good.
If it was on the side, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish never would
have said it's good. If it was on the top and less
than ten, there's no way רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would have said
it's bad. So what's the case? אלא לאו, ela lav, the only
way we can explain where there would have been a debate of
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is ביותר מעשר.
beyoser mi'eser. It was on the top, but it was more than
ten, and that seems to be the debate of ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Does a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach
work for more than ten? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
no, not necessarily. לעולם בעשר, le'olam b'eser, it was ten or less.
So what was the debate? So why did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say... so ומן הצד, u'min hatzad, and it was off to the
side, and that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it's no good.
So what did ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say? וברב חסדא קמיפלגי? uv'Rav
Chisda kamiflagi? Yes, maybe they debate רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Maybe ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish thinks that even on the side would count as
a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. Okay, so you hear here you have
a debate whether it works for שבת Shabbos or not, not clear
what the scenario is. The גמרא Gemara says, let's try to argue
they're debating whether צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach works bigger than ten. And
they say, no, maybe they debate whether צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach works
when the beam or the vine goes off on the side. Okay,
but now we're not done. ורמי דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן, v'rami deRabbi
Yochanan a'deRabbi Yochanan, we're going to show contradiction of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan against himself, ורמי דריש לקיש אדריש לקיש, v'rami deReish Lakish a'deReish
Lakish, and a contradiction of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish on himself. Okay,
where do you know this? דאמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה ברבי
חנינא, de'amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi Yehuda b'Rabbi Chanina, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says not in his own name, which will be significant in
a minute, but in the name of רבי יהושע ברבי חנינא. Rabbi
Yehoshua b'Rabbi Chanina. פאה מותרת לעניין כלאים. pea muteres le'inyan kilayim. פאה
pea with here does not mean a corner, it actually means like
a type of a braiding. רש"י Rashi says that's why also the
גמרא Gemara uses the phrase פאה pea to refer to a wig.
פאה נכרית pea nochris is a wig of another woman's hair. So
anyway, if you have a braiding which basically means is this, it
basically means you're stringing some type of a vine from one post
to another, that's okay for כלאים kilayim אבל לא לשבת, aval lo
leShabbos, not for שבת. Shabbos. Now before we said in our case
about the כלאים, kilayim, the ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said it was
good for both. Here he's saying it works for כלאים kilayim and
it doesn't work for שבת. Shabbos. So we must be talking about
some different type of a scenario. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, כמחיצות לשבת דלא כך מחיצות לכלאים דלא.
kemechitzos leShabbos delo kach mechitzos le'kilayim delo. The same way it doesn't
work for שבת, Shabbos, it doesn't work for כלאים. kilayim. So here
everybody is one degree stricter than they were before. Before ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish said it's good for both and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said it's good for only כלאים. kilayim. Here ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says it's only good for כלאים kilayim and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says it's good for nothing. So they're contradicting their previous positions. So
the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא דריש לקיש אדריש לקיש לא קשיא, bishlama
deReish Lakish a'deReish Lakish lo kashya, I get that ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish isn't contradicting himself, הא דידיה הא דרביה. ha deidei ha derabeih.
The first position he said in his own name, that it was
good for both. Here where he says it's no good for שבת,
Shabbos, he said in the name of his רבי, rebe, because it
said ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said in the name of רבי יהודה
ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Yehuda b'Rabbi Chanina. So that doesn't bother us. But
אלא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן קשיא, ela d'Rabbi Yochanan ad'Rabbi Yochanan kashya,
we've got a problem. In the first ברייתא braisa with the whole
כלאים kilayim and the vine, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said is good
for כלאים kilayim not for שבת. Shabbos. Here he says it's not
good for either. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, here's how
we can try to reconcile
it.
Excuse me.
אי אמרת בשלמא התם, i amarta bishlama hasam, if you say I
can make sense or it'll make sense over there the first case
where he said yes כלאים, kilayim, no שבת, Shabbos, that's על גבן,
al gaban, that was because the vine went on top and therefore
he said good for כלאים, kilayim, not good for שבת Shabbos because
it's too wide. That's what we were trying to argue that he
said too wide, that was the problem. So that's why he split
his vote. הכא hacha and here where he says it's not good
for either, it's מן הצד, min hatzad, it's because off it's because
it's on the side, and on the side it wouldn't even be
good for כלאים. kilayim. שפיר, shapir, then I can explain. Okay, so
basically we had one case with these vines and the posts, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said good for כלאים, kilayim, not for שבת. Shabbos.
We have another case he said not good for either. The גמרא
Gemara says you know, here's how I can make sense. The first
case the issue was it was too wide, that's only a שבת
Shabbos problem. The second case it was on the side, not on
top, and that's a problem in שבת Shabbos and כלאים. kilayim. And
if you take that interpretation it shows that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says when it's too wide it's not good for שבת. Shabbos. That's
how I would like to read it. אלא אי אמרת אידי ואידי
מן הצד, ela i amarta aidi v'aidi min hatzad, but you said
that the case he said no good for שבת, Shabbos, yes good
for כלאים kilayim was when it was on the side. If that's
the case מאי למימרא, mai l'meimra, then what's this case talking about
where he says it's not good for either? If he's already said
that when it's on the side it is good for כלאים. kilayim.
The גמרא Gemara says לעולם אידי ואידי מן הצד, l'olam aidi v'aidi
min hatzad, you know what I'm going to stick to my guns
says the גמרא. Gemara. לעולם אידי ואידי מן הצד, l'olam aidi v'aidi
min hatzad, both cases they're off to the side. So why in
one case do you say it works for כלאים kilayim and the
other case you say it doesn't work for כלאים? kilayim? התם בעשרה
הכא ביותר מעשרה. hasam b'asara hacha b'yosair m'asara. More than ten is
a problem, yes, when you combine it with being off to the
side. So here the גמרא Gemara is resisting saying that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is in רב's Rav camp. רב Rav says more than
ten is no good. Here we see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
has a problem with this כלאים kilayim case that it doesn't work
for שבת. Shabbos. So we want to say maybe it's because he
holds like רב Rav that more than ten is no good. But
the גמרא's Gemara pushing back and say no, we want to say
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan actually says more than ten is okay
by שבת. Shabbos. What's going on here? Here the only reason it's
a problem was it was off to the side. Off to the
side is no good for שבת. Shabbos. Is it good for כלאים?
kilayim? Here's where more or less than ten makes a difference. With
less than ten it works for כלאים, kilayim, more than ten it
does not. Okay, so yes, that might make a difference, but only
when it's already off to the side. If it's a normal צורת
הפתח, tzuras hapesach, it's fine no matter how big it is. And
now the גמרא Gemara says ומנא תימרא דשאני לן בין עשרה ליתר
מעשרה, u'mna teimra d'shani lan bein asara l'yosair m'asara, how do I
know that it matters more or less than ten again when it's
off to the side for
כלאים kilayim purposes? דאמר
ליה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש.
d'amar lei Rabbi
Yochanan l'Resh Lakish. Sorry. Right,
because they were debating whether it worked for כלאים kilayim or not.
So he said to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, לאו כך היה מעשה,
lav kach haya maaseh, wasn't there a story שהלך רבי יהושע אצל
רבי יוחנן בן נורי ללמוד תורה, she'halach Rabbi Yehoshua eitzel Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri lilmod Torah, that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua went to רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri to learn תורה, Torah, אף
על פי שבקי בהלכות כלאים, af al pi she'baki b'hilchos kilayim, and
even though רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was an expert in laws of
כלאים, kilayim, he nevertheless wanted to learn it from רבי יוחנן בן
נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. ומצאו, u'm'tzao, and he found רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri שיושב בין האילנות, she'yosheiv bein ha'ilanos,
that he was sitting between the trees, ומתח זמורה מאילן לאילן, u'masach
zmora m'ilan l'ilan, and he had stretched a vine from one tree
to the other and that was the area he was sitting in.
So he said oh what a great opportunity to ask him a
question about הלכות כלאים. hilchos kilayim. ואמר לו, v'amar lo, so רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said to רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, רבי גפנים כאן מהו לזרוע כאן, rebbi gefanim kan mahu lizroa
kan, rebbi if there were vines planted on this side of you
know the area that you had framed with these with the trees
and the vine, could you plant another crop on the other side?
Right, great opportunity. I came to learn הלכות כלאים. hilchos kilayim. He's
sitting here with these posts and these vines. Let me ask him
what would be the הלכה halacha here if it was a כלאים
kilayim question.
And he says this is the גמרא Gemara over here. אמר לו,
amar lo, he says to him he says to him יאמינו לו
ya'aminu lo I'm reading a
novel. אמר לו, amar lo, no. בעשרה מותר ביותר מעשרה אסור. b'asara
mutar b'yosair m'asara assur. Up to ten it would be fine. If
they were bigger than ten it would be no good. Now now
we want to say that that difference makes a makes a difference
by כלאים kilayim when it's off to the side rather than on
top. That's now what the גמרא's Gemara going to now add to
it. במאי, b'mai, now what's the
case? במאי עסקינן, b'mai askinan, what's the case? אילימא על גבן, eilima
al gaban, if we're talking that the that the vine is on
top, יותר מעשרה אסור, yosair m'asara assur, can you would you really
think that bigger than ten is a problem by כלאים? kilayim? Meaning
when we were debating bigger than ten that was by שבת, Shabbos,
but by כלאים kilayim clearly that's okay if it's done with the
with the string on top. How do you know? והתניא, v'hatanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. braisa. היו שם קנים
הדוקרנין hayu sham kanim hadukranin you had there posts that were
banged into the ground ועשה
להן פאה מלמעלה v'asah lahen peah milmalah and you made a string
running on top of the posts אפילו ביותר מעשר מותר afillu b'yoter
me'eser mutar it’s an explicit ברייתא braita that says even bigger than
ten. So basically what we know is we’re debating כלאים kilayim is
clearly as you see from this more lenient than שבת Shabbos regarding
this issue of what constitutes a division. Okay probably because just if
you want one conceptual reason why כלאים kilayim should be more lenient
is by שבת Shabbos you have to define a domain. You have
to enclose the entire space and define it as a domain whereas
by כלאים kilayim you only have to separate one side from the
next side. You really need a wall you don’t need a domain
so anyway conceptually it’s not demanding as much as שבת. Shabbos. Right
well not the כלאים. kilayim. No the שבת. Shabbos. You think it
would be a little more lenient. I understand which is why I’m
giving you a conceptual reason why it’s different because it’s not just
about דרבנן derabbanan דאורייתא. deoraisa. So we were debating by כלאים kilayim
by שבת Shabbos whether bigger than ten was a problem or not.
But we have an explicit teaching by כלאים kilayim that bigger than
ten is okay. And even though we know that bigger than ten
is okay here ר׳ יוחנן בן נורי Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri made
a distinction bigger than ten and less than ten. So the only
way that could matter is that it’s not a classic צורת הפתח.
tzuras hapesach. The string didn’t go on top the string went on
the side. And that’s how the גמרא Gemara concludes אלא לאו שמע
מינה אלא לאו מן הצד. ela lav shma mina ela lav min
hatzad. So if it’s a problem bigger than ten by כלאים kilayim
it would only be because the string went on the side וקאמר
ליה דעשר מותר יותר מעשר אסור v’ka’amar lei d’eser mutar yoter me’eser
assur and you see that up to ten is okay bigger than
ten is a problem שמע מינה shma mina that’s a good conclusion.
So where are we left with all of this? What we see
is that כלאים kilayim is more lenient by the way we see
that by כלאים kilayim the גמרא Gemara concludes number one bigger than
ten is okay if it’s a classic צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. If
it’s off to the side then possibly there’s a distinction between smaller
than ten being good up to ten being good bigger than ten
being no good. So there’s a debate of ר׳ יוחנן וריש לקיש
Rebbi Yochanan v’Reish Lakish whether this certain setup that they had by
כלאים kilayim would work by שבת Shabbos what was the debate? So
the גמרא Gemara says it could be the debate was because it
worked מן הצד. min hatzad. Maybe ר׳ יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbi Yochanan
v’Reish Lakish is so lenient that he allows even by שבת Shabbos
a צורת הפתח מן הצד? tzuras hapesach min hatzad? ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan says no it has to be on the top. And the
issues here was so ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said it wasn’t good
for שבת Shabbos because it was off to the side and not
only that it won’t even be good for כלאים kilayim if it’s
off to the side if it’s bigger than ten. So that was
the issues that was going on here that was all from the
side. If it was actually on the top can it be bigger
than ten? רב Rav says no the משנה mishnah that we have
says yes. And the גמרא Gemara tried to say that ר׳ יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan would agree with רב Rav but in the end could
not prove that. So in the end you have רב Rav saying
bigger than ten is no good you have ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
not necessarily siding with רב Rav and still unclear what the conclusion
is. And as I told you this is the big issue. The
רמב״ם Rambam rules like רב Rav and the רמב״ם Rambam says bigger
than ten צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach does not work. And therefore and
you cannot have it in any modern scenario except as Charlie told
us took 180 years or whatever they made one in one place
but anyway we rule that bigger than ten is good and also
the גמרא Gemara also didn’t know that if bigger than ten is
no good how about when it’s פרוץ מרובה parutz merubah when it’s
mostly unwalled. So again our עירובים eiruvin assume both of those leniencies
bigger than ten is okay mostly unwalled is okay and that’s how
we create עירובים eiruvin with all צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach yes.
Is it or maybe not isn’t רב Rav here seemingly the דעת
יחיד? daas yachid? So then why would anyone why would anyone want
to פסקן pasken like him?
Well it starts off with a דעת יחיד daas yachid but then
it has ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan siding with him and then it
has אמוראים Amoraim trying to explain the implications of
רב. Rav. So it’s not necessarily so clear that’s why there’s often
a debate. Okay so now yes.
When we say on the top do we really mean it has
to be like ממש mamash on the top or within three sort
of say the same idea three sort of like the top or?
No it has to be directly over. It can't be within three.
If it’s yeah it could be directly over but it can't be
off to the side within three. No in the middle but like
three from the top is still no good so that? What?
Like that's saying literally directly smack if this is the top and
you just made it the same flush but just within three? No
I’m saying no it has to go over the top. It cannot
go it cannot be it cannot be touch against banged into the
side. So you don’t say any לבוד? lavud? Correct. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues גופא gufa אמר רב חסדא. amar Rav Chisda.
Now we get to the what a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach looks
like. אמר רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda צורת הפתח שעשה מן הצד
לא עשה ולא כלום. tzuras hapesach she’asah min hatzad lo asah v’lo
klum. If the the post on the top goes on the side
not directly over the top it’s no good.
ואמר רב חסדא v’amar Rav Chisda אמר רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda
צורת הפתח שאמרו צריכה שתהא בריאה כדי להעמיד בה דלת. tzuras hapesach
she’amru tzerichah shetehei b’riah k’dei le’amid bah deles. Interesting it can’t be
completely fictional as it
were it has
to be strong enough this doorframe that it could support a door
that it could support a door. actually leaned a door against it,
it wouldn't break and collapse. Okay, but ואפילו דלת של קשים *Va'afilu
delet shel kashim*. On the other hand, the door could be made
out of straw, like building your house out of straw, like the
three little pigs. Okay. But it cannot be so thin that it
would collapse if any weight was put on it. So it says
it has to be עומד ברוח מצויה *omed beruach metzuyah*. Right. Well,
that's an interesting question. That maybe yes, we already saw before that
if something would be blown away by wind, it would not be
good. אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי ינאי *Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi
Yannai*. So now it says in the name of רבי ינאי *Rabbi
Yannai*, צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach? צריכה היכר ציר *tzurath hapesach tzerichah heker
tzir*. He's going to push it even further. It's not enough that
it's just a post and a beam. It actually has to have
something that's basically is like a hinge. It has to have a
symbol of a hinge, something that indicates that you could put a
hinge a door onto it. So, מאי היכר ציר *mai heker tzir*,
what does that mean something that like indicates a hinge? אמר רב
אביא אף כסא *Amar Rav Avya af kissa*. אף כסא *Af kissa*,
which basically sounds like it's the, you know, it's the things you
have there that attaches to the door, which is basically like the
hole, you know, the loops that you would put the peg of
the hinge into. So it's the part that attaches to the frame,
right? Not the hinge itself, right? If this is your doorframe, you
know, you've got like this part, so that if you were to
come put a door in, right, the hinge of the door would
go like, you know, the hinge of the door would go into
it like that. So you actually need, you know, whatever that's called,
but the part through which you put the hinge. So for him
it really has to look like a doorframe. It's not just like
symbolic. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. We don't
פסקן *pasken* that way. אשכחינהו רב אחא בריה דרב אביא לתלמידי דרב
אשי *Ashkechinhu Rav Acha breih deRav Avya letalmidei deRav Ashi*.
Right, if we did, can you imagine how much more work it
would take? All of our posts that we bang into the telephone
poles would have to have little hinge things on them. Anyway, the
בריאה *briyah* we do פסקן *pasken*, but okay. בריאה *Briyah*, how long,
how strong does it have to be for a straw door? Anyway,
רב אחא *Rav Acha* the son of רב אביא *Rav Avya* found
the תלמידי דרב אשי *talmidei deRav Ashi*, the students of רב אשי
*Rav Ashi*. אמר להו *Amar lehu* when he said to them, אמר
מר מידי בצורת הפתח *amar mar midi betzurath hapesach*, did the master
say anything regarding the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach *tzurath hapesach*, any thing
about special criteria? אמרו ליה לא lo, לא lo, אמר ולא כלום
v’lo klum, *Amru leih lo lo amar velo kloom*. They said no,
he didn't say anything. Okay, that's the end of that discussion. Now,
that's a very bizarre line of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. What? So
someone read it that since he didn't say anything, we can infer
that he doesn't need this special criteria because he said, you know,
okay צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach *tzurath hapesach*. Did he add anything to
that? No, he didn't add anything. Okay, so you don't need a
היכר ציר *heker tzir*. All right. So, all right, now, תנא *tana*,
we taught in a ברייתא braita: *Beraita*. צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach שאמרו
*tzurath hapesach she'amru*. This צורת הפתח tzurat ha-petach, *tzurath hapesach*, now we're
going to get to being very specific what it is. קנה מכאן
וקנה מכאן *kaneh mikan vekaneh mikan*, a post on one side, a
post on the other side, וקנה על גביהן *vekaneh al gabeihen*, and
a post or a beam over them. Okay, basically as we've been
describing. Now, צריכין ליגע או אין In, צריכין ליגע *tzerichin liga o
ein tzerichin liga*. Now, here's a key question, also very relevant for
our telephone posts. Does the beams on the side, the posts on
the side have to come in contact with the beam above? Right,
we don't do it. The telephone wires are like thirty feet up
there and we've got this little post down here and we imagine
that as long as it's directly underneath, that defines the frame. But
that was what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking. You wouldn't have
logically said that. Logically you would have said it has to come
in contact, it has to be a full frame. Why would you
think it wouldn't have? So anyway, well, let's take a look. So
does it have to touch or not? רב נחמן אמר אין צריכין
ליגע *Rav Nachman amar ein tzerichin liga*, it does not. ורב ששת
אמר צריכין ליגע *veRav Sheshet amar tzerichin liga*, it does have to
touch. אזל רב נחמן *Azal Rav Nachman*, who said it doesn't, ועבד
עובדא בי ריש גלותא כשמעתיה *ve'avad uvda bei Reish Galuta kishmateih*. He
ruled, he enacted his פסק *psak* in the house of the ריש
גלותא *Reish Galuta*. They asked him to set up their courtyard or
whatever so that they can, you know, presumably they could carry, maybe
it had an opening bigger than ten אמות *amot*. So he made
a צורת הפתח *tzurath hapesach* and he made it without the posts
touching the beam above. אמר ליה Amar lei, רב ששת Rav Sheshet
*Amar leih Rav Sheshet*, who said it has to touch the beam
above, לשמעיה *lishmeih*, he said to his attendant, רב גדא *Rav Gadda*,
name was רב גדא *Rav Gadda*. זיל שלוף אתינו *Zil shlof atinu*.
Go tear it down, throw it out. Meaning, so now that's pretty
dangerous besides that he's got, you know, somebody who has a legitimate
position opposite him. Here he is, he's invalidating the צורת הפתח *tzurath
hapesach* in the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*. Okay, you
don't want to be fooling around in the house of the ריש
גלותא *Reish Galuta*. You just contravened your colleague. I understand. So anyway,
I don't know what was going on there. אזל *Azal*, maybe he
really thought like there's a total error. Anyway, אזל שלוף אתינו *azal
shlof atinu*, so רב גדא *Rav Gadda* went, he tore it down
and threw it out. אשכחוהו דבי ריש גלותא *Ashkechuhu d'bei Reish Galuta*.
So the people of the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*
saw what he was doing. חבשוהו *Chavshuhu*, and so they threw him
into jail, they bound him up. Okay, what are you doing tearing
down our great עירוב Eruv *eruv*? אזל רב ששת *Azal Rav Sheshet*,
so רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* went, he heard that his attendant was
being held. קם אבבא *Kam abava*, he went by the door. אמר
ליה Amar lei, גדא גדא פוק תא *Amar leih Gadda Gadda puk
ta*, which was his name, come, you know, get out, come to
me. נפק ואתא *Nafak ve'ata*, he got out
and he came. Which is bizarre. What was it? Was it like
magic? Was it some say that he was. I don't know why
then רב ששת didn't get into trouble. Anyway, this is a Talmudic
precedent for tearing down an עירוב you don't like. There you go,
it really is. Anyway, okay. אתא לגבי רב ששת Ata legabei Rav
Sheshet and now רב ששת who was the one obviously who felt
very strongly about his position that it was no good. He found
רבה בר שמואל. Rabbah bar Shmuel. אמר ליה, תני מר מידי בצורת
הפתח? Tani Mar midei b'tzurat hapetach? Similar to the previous discussion, right,
trying to find if there's more evidence to bring to the discussion.
Have you taught any interesting ברייתות braitot about צורת הפתח? אמר ליה,
אין, yes, תנינא, Tanina, we taught in a ברייתא: כיפה. Kippah. If
you have a כיפה kippah which is an arch, so you have
a nice little picture there in רש״י. Rashi. רבי מאיר מחייב במזוזה.
Rabbi Meir mechayev b'mezuzah. Rabbi Meir says it's obligated in a מזוזה.
mezuzah. Now this is not exactly about צורת הפתח for שבת, Shabbat,
but we're going to see you can apply it. The same question
is, what do you define as a door? So if you have
this arch, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're obligated in a מזוזה,
mezuzah, וחכמים פוטרין ve’chachamim potrin and the חכמים Chachamim say you're exempt.
Now, now how is that relevant? ושוין שאם יש ברגליה עשרה שהיא
חייבת. Ve’shavin she’im yesh b’ragleha asarah she’hi chayavet. It goes up ten
טפחים tfachim and it's four טפחים tfachim wide. Okay? The definition of
a doorframe, minimum definition is, and this is why by the way
the beams that we make for the צורת הפתח have to be
ten טפחים tfachim high. The minimum definition of a doorframe is ten
טפחים. tfachim. טפח Tefach is about three inches, by four טפחים. tfachim.
Okay? That's your minimum definition of a doorframe. Less than that, you
would not be obligated in a מזוזה, mezuzah, less than that it
would not count as a צורת הפתח for שבת. Shabbat. So what
you have is you've got an arch. Okay? But the arch basically
if it goes first ten טפחים tfachim by four טפחים tfachim wide,
so obviously you're okay. You've got your good doorframe there. The question
is what happens if it starts arching before it hit the ten
טפחים tfachim and therefore part of it does not go the whole
four טפחים tfachim wide. Okay? That's the debate. So we're going to
see how this will be relevant in a minute. ושוין שאם יש
ברגליה עשרה שהיא חייבת. Ve’shavin she’im yesh b’ragleha asarah she’hi chayavet. אמר
אביי. Amar Abaye. Now אביי Abaye is going to explain what the
debate is about. הכל מודים אם גבוה עשרה ואין ברגלה שלושה. Hakol
modim im gavo’ah asarah v’ein b’raglah sheloshah. Everybody agrees that even if
the whole thing is ten טפחים, tfachim, if it doesn't start with
three טפחים tfachim straight, it's no good. I'll describe it in a
minute, let me just read it. אי נמי או יש ברגלה שלושה.
Ei nami o yesh b’raglah sheloshah. It starts with three טפחים tfachim
straight, ואין גבוה עשרה, v'ein gavo’ah asarah, and it's not ten high,
ולא כלום, it's nothing. So he says like this. He says look.
Here's two scenarios where everybody will agree that it's no good. If
you have something that even before it gets to be three טפחים,
tfachim, it starts arching, okay, one wonders how you can fit under
it, but let's say it's a narrow arch. So here it's four,
right, and then it starts—suddenly becomes 3.9—and it doesn't even get to
be three טפחים tfachim before it starts arching, then it's nothing. Then
you know you don't even have the beginning of a doorframe before
you get off of essentially ground level. So everybody agrees that's no
good. Certainly everybody agrees that if the whole thing here is, you
know, is less than ten טפחים, tfachim, it's no good either. Okay?
But the case that we're debating is the following. Is the first
three טפחים? tfachim? It starts with being three by four. Okay? So
you have the beginning of a doorframe. It has the right width
and it's off of the ground level. And then afterwards it starts
arching. Okay? You know maybe whatever, maybe make it a little bit
more in there. Afterwards it starts arching. And so here it starts
becoming 3.9, it's less. Now how is that going to be good?
You know when it's up to ten טפחים, tfachim, it's not four
טפחים tfachim wide. So here is the debate. So here's the debate.
כי פליגי ביש ברגלה גימל וגבוה עשרה. Ki peligi b’yesh b’raglah gimal
v’gavo’ah asarah. It's the first three טפחים tfachim off the ground, it's
also four טפחים tfachim wide. So you have the start of a
doorframe. And the whole thing is ten טפחים tfachim high. ואין רחבה
ארבעה. V'ein rechavah arba’ah. But it's not after it gets the first
three טפחים tfachim off the ground, it's not four טפחים tfachim wide.
But ויש בה לחוק ולהשלימה לארבעה. v'yesh bah lachok u’l’hashlimah l’arba’ah. In
theory you could carve it out. So it's not just an arch
like this. It actually is a structure like this. Okay? So although
here at the ten טפח tefach point, you know who knows, maybe
it's only two טפחים tfachim wide, right, this is what the arch
looks like, okay, but in theory you have enough structure there you
could carve it out and you could just continue from the bottom
three טפחים tfachim and if you kept that as a you know
and you made a rectangular arch and you just continued—the bottom was
the right parameters, it was the first three טפחים tfachim it was
four wide, so there's enough material there that you can carve it
out. be okay. Okay so is that good or not? So רבי
מאיר סבר *Rebbi Meir savar*, רבי מאיר סבר חוקקים להשלים *Rebbi Meir
savar chokekim lehashlim*, you, you carve out to finish it. The beginning
of the first three טפחים *tefachim* were good. If you had continued
that way, you would have had a defined doorway. So you can
envision it as if it's been carved out. And therefore, because it's,
you know, the idea of having these parameters is not like is
to define conceptually that it's a doorway. So for him, the fact
that it has that, you know, it starts with that shape and
in theory it could finish, that potential is enough to give it
the status of a doorway. It's, you know, you have that thing
sometimes, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like כל העומד לזרוק lizrok כזרוק
דמי *kol ha-omed lizrok k'zaruk dami*, that you look at the potential.
So the fact that it's that big and in theory could be
carved out is enough to define that this is a doorway. That's
what רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says. וחכמים סברי *ve-Chachamim savri* and the
Rabbis say, רבנן סברי אין חוקקים להשלים *Rabbanan savri ein chokekim lehashlim*
that you don't do it. It's sort of like, you know, I
like quoting this line that they asked Michelangelo, right, how did he
carve out the David? So he says I just cut away everything
that wasn't David. You know, I started with a big block. So
he cut away everything that isn't a פתח *petach* and then you
have your פתח *petach*. Okay, anyway. So that's the debate, is it
good if that it doesn't have the right space there, but in
theory you could carve it out and it's got the beginning of
the right space. Now, how is this relevant for us? Here's how
it's relevant. Because where is the upper beam of this door? The
upper beam here of this door is, right, the upper beam here
is not connected to the actual, you know, to the actual walls.
Meaning the walls here, right, the upper beam, you know, the flat
part of it, this is essentially like a case where the posts
don't reach the top. You know, because, I mean I guess if
you actually carved it out it would, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is imagining that if this works, it works even though the real
posts here don't reach the top according to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*.
Okay. So what constitutes the top, even let's say, I know if
you would carve it out or something, this would be the top
but the actual currently existing posts don't reach it. And that still
it's good. So this seems to be a confirmation of the idea
that it's not important in practice that the posts reach the top.
So this is what he said to רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*. So
אמר ליה *amar leh*, so רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* was the one
that insisted the posts reach the top and really stood up for
his position in the house of ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*. So he
said to him, אי משכחת להו *im mashchachas lehu* if you find
the people of the house of ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*, לא תימרו
להו לבי ריש גלותא ולא מידי מהא מתניתא דכיפה *lo teimru lehu
le-vei Reish Galuta velo midi me-ha matnita de-kippah*. Don't tell them anything
about this מתניתא דכיפה *matnita de-kippah*, it's going to get me even
more in trouble because they're going to realize that my position is
actually contradicted by this ברייתא *baraita* and I just had a whole
tussle with them about my position. Okay. Yes. So צורת הפתח לא
עושה שהיא צריכה לעשות מזוזה שם *tzorat ha-petach lo osah she-hi tzrichah
la'asot mezuzah sham*? What? צורת הפתח *tzorat ha-petach* you have to put
on a מזוזה *mezuzah* there? Oh, if you have a צורת הפתח
*tzorat ha-petach* there, no because it's not like a בית דירה *beit
dira*. Okay, but it's only צורת הפתח *tzorat ha-petach* that is actually
in בית דירה *beit dira*. Yeah, but this isn't a, yeah, it's
an interesting point, but that's not how these things are functioning. Yeah.
And to get back to it. So although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
didn't conclude whether you need it to go to the top or
not, you're saying practice is what we hold that you don't need
to. Correct. And the reason is because it's as if it's extending
to the top sort of. Yeah. So, yeah, and enough that it
has the shape, the right pieces are there even if they're not
connected. And that's what it's trying to prove by here. You know,
even if you say it's as if it's carved out or whatever,
in practice the pieces aren't connected. And even if the pieces aren't
connected, it's still... No matter how high from the top it is.
Yeah. Well, the question is more than עשרים אמות *esrim amot*. But,
you know, we don't say like לבוד *lavud*, you know, like a
לבוד *lavud* kind of thing, like within three whatever, three whatever it
is, five whatever. Correct. Correct. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. Next משנה *mishna*. And now it's a nice little continuation because
we are continuing talking about practically what the, we talked about practically
what the צורת הפתח *tzorat ha-petach* looks like. Now we're going to
talk about practically what's required in terms of the לחי lechi *lechi*
or קורה kora, *korah*. הכשר מבוי mavoi, *hechsher mavoi*, what do you
need to validate a מבוי *mavoi*? Which is what our first משנה
*mishna* talked about. בית שמאי אומרים לחי וקורה Beit Shammai omrim lechi
ve-kora, *Beit Shammai omrim lechi ve-korah*, you actually need both components, both
the horizontal, both the vertical and the horizontal. בית הלל אומרים או
לחי או קורה Beit Hillel omrim o lechi o kora, *Beit Hillel
omrim o lechi o korah*, either the לחי lechi *lechi* or the
קורה kora, *korah*, which is what we've been assuming. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer אומר לחיים lechis. *Rebbi Eliezer omer lechayayim*. רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer*
says you need a לחי lechi *lechi* on each side. משום רבי
ישמעאל אמר תלמיד אחד לפני רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *mishum Rebbi Yishmael
amar talmid echad lifnei Rebbi Akiva*, in the name of רבי ישמעאל
*Rebbi Yishmael* a certain תלמיד *talmid* said in front of רבי עקיבא
*Rebbi Akiva*, לא נחלקו בית שמאי Beit Shammai ובית הלל על מבוי
שהוא פחות מארבע אמות שניתר או בלחי או בקורה *lo nechelku Beit
Shammai ve-Beit Hillel al mavoi she-hu pachot me-arba amot she-nittar o be-lechi
o be-korah*. There was never a debate if it was less than
ארבע אמות *arba amot* wide that a לחי lechi *lechi* or קורה
kora *korah* would suffice. על מה נחלקו *al mah nechelku*, where was
the debate? על רחב מארבע אמות עד עשר *al rachav me-arba amot
ad esser*, if it's wider than ארבע אמות *arba amot* up to
עשר *esser*, because עשר *esser* we know is a... So that was
the debate between four and ten. שבית שמאי אומרים לחי lechi וקורה,
and there it's like we think, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you
need both, a לחי lechi and a קורה, kora and בית הלל
Beit Hillel says or לחי lechi or קורה, kora. one or the
other. So basically, it just says בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית
שמאי Beit Shammai agreed less than four. אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi
Akiva, and רבי עקיבא said על זה וזה נחלקו: al zeh ve-zeh
necheleku: no, even less than four they debated. Okay. So you have
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai plus the position
here of רבי אליעזר that says two לחיים. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: כמאן? keman? Who is this going like that
a לחי lechi or קורה kora suffices? דלא כחנניה ולא כתנא קמא.
de-lo ke-Chananya ve-lo ke-Tanaya kamma. We're assuming that this issue about what
would be good would be even with a מבוי מפולש, mavoi mefulash,
even if it was open at both ends. Now you might remember
that we said that if it's open at both ends, one end
needs at least a צורת הפתח, maybe even more, maybe even actually
a door. So the גמרא Gemara says this is not like either
of those, this says a לחי lechi or קורה kora? is enough.
So there's an obvious answer. אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר: amar Rav
Yehuda hachi kama: this is what it means. הכשר מבוי סתום כיצד?
hechshar mavoi satum keitzad? If it's a closed, if it's a dead-end
מבוי, it's only open at one end, how much do you need?
Not if it's open at two ends. בית שמאי אומרים לחי וקורה,
Beit Shammai omrim lechi ve-kora, ובית הלל אומרים או לחי או קורה.
u-Beit Hillel omrim o lechi o kora. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
has an interesting analysis of what this debate is about. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai אומרים לחי וקורה, you need both a לחי and a
קורה. kora, So the גמרא Gemara assumes that if you need both,
that really defines it as a full wall on that side. So
if בית שמאי Beit Shammai. needs a full wall on the fourth
side, the גמרא Gemara says that that sounds like למימרא דקסבר בית
שמאי, le-maimra de-kasavar Beit Shammai, ארבע מחיצות דאורייתא, arba mechitzos de-oraisa, that
biblically you need four walls, because a לחי and a קורה kora
must be to define it as a real full fourth wall. So
the גמרא says לא, לזרוק משלוש הוא דמיחייב. lizrok mi-shalosh hu de-michayiv.
No, maybe biblically if you threw into it, meaning when it says
לזרוק it's an example of what you would need to transgress. So
biblically to be a רשות היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, three walls would be
enough and if you threw from a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim into
it you would violate. So three walls might be enough biblically, but
לטלטל עד דאיכא ארבע. le-taltel ad de-ika arba. Why did they need
this fourth thing to be considered a full wall, a לחי and
a קורה? That's rabbinically to allow you to carry. So notice though
the גמרא is not rejecting its assumption. Its assumption is if you
need a לחי and a קורה, that's to really define it as
a wall. Remember we had a discussion before on מחיצה mechitza or
הכר, hekker, how was it functioning? Here the גמרא says if you
need both, clearly it functions as a wall. But it doesn't prove
that with three walls it's not biblically. Three walls could be רשות
היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, but rabbinically you need four walls to carry. And
the idea of both is to say a full wall. Let's just
do the flip side for בית הלל. Beit Hillel. בית הלל Beit
Hillel אומרים או לחי או קורה, one or the other. למימרא דקסבר
בית הלל שלוש מחיצות דאורייתא? la-maimra de-kasavar Beit Hillel shalosh mechitzos de-oraisa?
Since it's one or the other, clearly then this thing is not
a fourth wall, it's only like a הכר, hekker, it's only something
symbolic. So you see that three walls is biblically already a רשות
היחיד, reshut ha-yachid, and that seems to be a good argument if
we're going to let you carry in it, it must be a
רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid even though it only has three walls. גמרא
says לא, no, maybe they'd even be more lenient. Maybe לזרוק משתים
הוא דמיחייב. lizrok mi-shtayim hu de-michayiv. Now that's a really extreme position
which almost nobody holds up, but just it's possible to argue that
even two walls it's a רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. לטלטל עד דאיכא
שלוש. le-taltel ad de-ika shalosh. To carry you need three. So the
important thing the takeaway of this, the important thing is that the
גמרא conceptualizes the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי
of one or the other or do you need both, that if
you need both, it's defining it as a wall. If you need
one or the other, it's not defining it as a wall. You
will remember that that was debated before. Is לחי or קורה משום
מחיצה או משום הכר? mishum mechitza o mishum hekker? Here the גמרא
though is seeming to come down that with only one of those
it's a הכר. hekker. If it's both of those it's a מחיצה.
mechitza. But the גמרא is saying that doesn't prove what makes it
a biblical רשות. reshut. Biblical רשות reshut could be even less than
that. What we're talking about is what you need rabbinically in order
to carry, but conceptually is it a מחיצה mechitza or is it
a הכר hekker might be exactly the debate of בית הלל and
בית שמאי.